so we've made it so that our player
can jump in the scene and they look so
excited look at them go but a funny little
thing that you can do is because we're
just looking for whatever the space
bar is down the character just goes up in
fact if we just keep pressing space
bar our player will just fly off into
space it's very fitting we need to actually
fix that and we'll have to use some
of our coding skills to do so so in our
player controller we're going to create
a new variable and this one will be
public so we can see what it does and we're
going to use something called a bool
which is short for Boolean we'll get into
that in a bit but for now we'll call
it is on ground so that we know the
player is on the ground and we're going
to set this equal to true now a Boolean
value is another kind of data type
just like an integer is for a whole
numbers floats are for decimals a
bool is simply a value that holds true or
false this is particularly useful whenever
we have our conditional statements
that are trying to check if something
is true so what we can do is in our if
statement we can actually add some
code in here so for example when the space
bar is down this condition is true
and it'll add the player force to make the
player jump we can use two ampersand
symbols which if you hold shift and press 7
twice this means and and then if we type
is on ground so this means that whenever
the player is on the ground and whenever
they press the space bar we'll then
apply that force to make them jump
instead of letting them be able to fly off
into space one more thing that we're
going to add in our if statement is when
the player jumps we're going to
set is on ground to false so now in our
update function we'll know that when
the player jumps they're no longer on
the ground and so therefore because
is on ground is false this entire statement
will not be true and so it won't let you
actually jump again the only downside is
that we never actually set is on ground
back to true so we're actually going
to use our collisions again so since
we have a collider on the player and we
have colliders on the ground we know
that when the player touches the ground
that they've entered the collider box
for the ground so if we type private void
on collision enter and conveniently
visual studio auto completes for me the
entire method so I don't have to
write all that out myself so whenever the
player enters a collision with something
now we can set our is on ground
to true now if we save this and we go
back to unity and in our scene view we'll
bring our focus back to the player and
we'll get a better angle there you go so
we can watch this is on ground variable
down here this Boolean and right now
since it's true it's checked off we know
we're on the ground and when we press
space is on ground is unchecked when
we land back on the ground is on ground is
checked so it's another good reason
to jump for joy cool so now what you're
gonna do is you're going to create
your own Boolean variable called is on
ground and we're going to set that to
true in our if statement you're gonna use
two ampersand symbols remember hold shift
and seven and then you're going to add
is on ground so that way it's another
statement that also has to be true within
this if statement when the player
jumps you're going to set is on ground to
false and then using our colliders we
know when the players on the ground and
when they're not so you're going to
use the on collision enter method and then
you're going to set is on
ground back to true when
the player collides with
the ground now it's your turn